[inquisitive] So Sam, what's the deal with slideSonnet? Tell me about it!
[excited] Oh you're gonna LOVE this!
It takes your plain-text slides and turns them into fully narrated VIDEOS.
You just write slides, throw in some comments for narration, and SHAZZAM —
you get an MP4!
[skeptical] OK but WHY? ... Can't I just record myself talking over slides?
[dry humor] Sure, if you ENJOY sitting in a quiet room with a mic,
talking through EVERY ...
SINGLE ... slide till you get it right...
[sarcastic] And the BEST part — change one slide and you get to re-record it.
EVERY... SINGLE... TIME.
[enthusiastic] With slideSonnet,
your narration is just text sitting next to the code for your slides!
Edit a line, hit rebuild, DONE! No mic, no re-recording, no pain!
[intrigued] Alright, you've got my attention. How does it ACTUALLY work?
[confidently] Step one: write your slides.
In Markdown or in LaTeX, whatever floats your boat!
Step two: drop in "say" comments. Just text ... with the words you want spoken.
That's LITERALLY it!
[enthusiastic] Step three: run slidesonnet build.
It does the speech synthesis, renders your slides, and stitches it ALL together.
ONE command and you're done!
[eager] OK I want to try it! What do I do?
[confidently] Literally THREE commands.
pip install, INIT to set up a project template, and BUILD to make the video.
That's IT! [proudly] You'll have a narrated MP4 before your coffee gets cold!
[surprised] Hold on — the narration is LITERALLY JUST a comment in the Markdown?
[proudly] YEP! An HTML comment that starts with say colon.
The text inside becomes audio.
[excitement building] And here's the FUN part — what you're hearing RIGHT now?
[enthusiastic] Written EXACTLY this way!
[curious] So where does all the CONFIG STUFF go?
Voices, text-to-speech settings?
[enthusiastic] The playlist file is slide sonnet dot yaml.
It's got your text-to-speech backend, your voice mappings,
pronunciation dictionaries — the WHOLE deal!
[proudly] And slideSonnet finds it AUTOMATICALLY, so you hit build,
and everything else JUST WORKS!
[awe] Wait a SECOND!
[in wonder] THIS is how we're using different voices RIGHT NOW?
[playfully] YUP! You're alex, and I AM the default voice.
You just STICK a voice parameter in the say
comment and slideSonnet handles the rest!
[proudly] Pretty SLICK, right?
[curious] Can you do that thing where bullets pop in one at a time?
[confidently] Oh YEAH!
Just use star bullets instead of dashes and each one becomes a fragment!
[enthusiastic] Every fragment gets its own sub-slide and narration. EASY!
[enthusiastic] It ends up feeling JUST like a REAL talk —
ideas building one by one!
[wondering] What if I've got a slide that doesn't need any talking?
[casually] Easy. Nonarration gives you a quiet pause — nice for title cards.
And skip just HIDES the slide from the video completely. Great for drafts.
[conspiratorial] Oh, and FUN fact —
there's a skipped slide lurking at the END of this slide deck too!
[curious] What about the FANCY stuff — math? code? images?
[confidently] MARP has you COVERED.
[excited] Math, syntax-highlighted code, images — all standard Markdown,
no plugins.
And we've got pronunciation dictionaries too,
so names like Dijkstra and Euler ACTUALLY come out right!
[concerned] Doesn't cloud TTS get EXPENSIVE when you're still tweaking things?
[reassuringly] NAH, you don't need cloud for drafting. Use Piper — it's FREE!
runs locally. Throw in the preview flag for a quick rough cut.
[enthusiastic] And the BEST part? slideSonnet caches EVERYTHING!
Change one slide, only THAT slide rebuilds. Fast and cheap!
OK I'm SOLD. [excited] Let's DO this!
[warmly] THAT'S what I like to hear!
pip install slidesonnet, write some slides, add your say comments,
and hit build.
[enthusiastic] Now go and make SOMETHING AWESOME!